Guide to the Walter Crane Collection TAM 308
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Walter Crane Collection
1879-1915
TAM 308
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
0.25 Linear feet (1 box)
Walter Crane (1845-1915) was a British artist, illustrator, author, socialist and a participant in the Arts and Crafts movement. The collection contains illustrations, letters, postcards, a scrapbook, and a manuscript, "The Architecture of Art" (18 pp., [1887]).
Crane, Walter, 1845-1915.
Provenance
Gift of Albert Boni, April 8, 1971, who purchased these items in December 1970 from H. M. Fletcher Rare Books (London).
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Walter Crane (1845-1915) was a British artist, illustrator, author, socialist and a participant in the Arts and Crafts movement. His illustrations and political cartoons appeared widely in the labor and socialist press, literature, and printed ephemera, and he also provided illustrations for fine editions of classic and contemporary literature. In The Claims of Decorative Art (1892), he argued that art could not flourish in a world where wealth was unfairly distributed.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains autographed handwritten letters to Annie Besant, Harry Quilter, Edmund Russell, and to clients, with several letters containing references to his socialist beliefs, and a set of socialist postcards; a manuscript, "The Architecture of Art" ([1887], 18 p.); the "gesso collection," a set of drawings and illustrations by Crane and others, with accompanying notes, illustrative of and pertaining to the use of gesso (a white priming or ground…used to prepare [surfaces]… for painting, gilding, or other decorative processes); an advertising card for the Scottish Widows' Fund Mutual Life Assurance Society illustrated by Crane; and a scrapbook containing several illustrated clippings, a letter to John Page Hopps (contra the Boer War), several letters to clients (including one re: Crane's illustrations for Don Quixote), To Belgium, a poem and accompanying illustration, ca. 1914 (both by Crane), and a memorial article.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
I, Papers.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Two portfolios of drawings by Walter Crane can be found in the Non-Print collections of the Tamiment Library.
Besant, Annie Wood, 1847; Crane, Walter, 1845-1915. The architecture of art.; Crane, Walter, 1845-1915.; Hopps, John Page, 1834-1911.; Quilter, Harry, 1851-1907.; Russell, Edmund..; Advertising cards.; Arts and crafts movement--Great Britain.; Clippings (information artifacts); Decoration and ornament, Architectural.; Drawings.; Gesso.; Illustrations.; Letters (correspondence); Manuscripts for publication.; Postcards.; Scrapbooks.; Socialism and art--Great Britain.; Studies (visual works)
- Series I: Papers.
  - The Architecture of Art: Contents: Text of a lecture, first read at a meeting of the Architectural Association on Feb 18, 1887, and published in The Builder, Feb 26, 1887. A penciled annotation (probably by the book dealer who sold this material to Albert Boni) states "Original manuscript, 18 p., signed.", ca.1887 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Besant, Annie: Letters to (4) Contents: [a] Three letters written from Beaumont Lodge, Shepherd's Bush W. (London), dated: Jun 14, Aug 4 [1887], Feb 4, 1888. The first two concern his making a design for the cover of, 'your magazine Our Corne r' … 'as a help to your propaganda in the cause of socialism.' The third letter seeks assistance for Joseph Waddington, a Manchester workingman and socialist. [b] One letter written from Benares, India, Jan 23, 1904., 1887-1888, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bowers, Alfred: Letter to Contents: WC is 'glad' to subscribe to a testimonial for John Saunders, Aug 15, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brown, C.and E.: Letter to ("Such a design as that you indicate will cost…"), Mar 26, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings (9): Containing Drawings by WC, 1952-1963, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gesso Collection: The Dance: Frieze Panel in Gesso, Tinted with Lacquer. Walter Crane. Contents: As reproduced in The Architect, Dec 6, 1889 [From the Arts and Crafts Exhibition, 1889]. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustrations Contents: 5 images on three pieces of paper, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustration: "An Atlas of Astronomy" by Sir Robert Stawel Hall [sic: correct middle, last name = Stawell Ball]. London, George Philip and Son. Contents: Image: man holding hemisphere on shoulders, and surrounded by the signs of the zodiac [blue ink, white, green background]., 1892 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustration: "The Diamond Jubilee Commemoration of Her Majesty the Queen, 1897" [printed version] Contents: Image, on Union Jack background, two black ink-drawn figures, male and female, both in armor. Accompanied by panel with text [red, white, and blue; 6 x 9", mounted on board]. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustration: "The Treatment of Form in Gesso Decoration" Contents: Image, woman in classical Greek dress painting an illustration typical of that used at the head of a chapter in an illuminated manuscript [white and brown; 7 x 9" on tan tissue paper mounted on larger card stock], Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustration, Untitled Contents: Two cherubim [?], facing, seated on horses [white on dark blue or black; 3 x 5.5", mounted on larger card stock], Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gesso Collection: Illustrations [by others] - Early Italian Gesso Work, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gesso Collection: Notes on Gesso (by WC), Feb 1893, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Leaflet: "Children's Sunday [Sunday, Sep 1, 1912]" Containing drawing by WC. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Nutt, W. D.: Letter to Contents: Apparently in response to a query regarding friezes., Jan 4, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Postcards. Published for Newcastle Socialist Society, by Permission of Walter Crane. Set of 7, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Quilter, Harry: Letters to (9) Contents: [a] six letters written from Beaumont Lodge, Shepherd's Bush (London), dated: May 21, Jun 17, Jul 22, Oct 31, Nov 16 (1888), Nov 14 (1889); [b] one letter written on the letterhead of the Arts and Crafts Exhibition Society, Nov 5, 1888; [c] two letters written from 13 Holland St., Kensington (London), Nov 18, Nov 22 (1898)., 1888-1889, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Russell, Edmund: Letter to, Sep 22, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Scottish Widows' Fund Mutual Life Assurance Society Card (2.5 x 6") Containing drawing by WC, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook: Bifolio 1: "Dear Thomas" [Hutchinson?] Contents: "I am sending you a water-color sketch as a small contribution to the [?] bazaar in aid of the London hospital", Jun 24, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbook: Bifolio 2: Clippings Contents: [a] To Belgium (poem and accompanying drawing, both by WC), ca.1914; [b] five catalog announcements for the sale of WC items, undated., ca.1914, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Scrapbook: Bifolio 3: Letters and Clippings Contents: [a] to "Dear Mr. K[…] Parkes[?], Jul 22, 1899; [b] "My Dear Sir" [J.H. Sutherland Jackson], Jan 16, 1903; [c] "Picture by Walter Crane from Household Stories from Grimm [clipping], undated; [d] "The death of Mr. Walter Crane, who passed away suddenly…" [clipping], undated, ca.1899-1915, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Scrapbook: Loose Letters (4) Contents: [a] to "Dear Mr. Hollyer" undated; [b] to [M. Bergerat] re MB's request for a contribution to a project/publication titled "La Vie Moderne," Jun 8, 1879; [c] to John Page Hopps, re gathering signatures of critics of the South African War [aka Boer War], Jun 15, 1902; [d] to Thomas Hutchinson, Aug 17, 1904 [from Normandy]., 1879-1904, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - [Sherratt?] and Hughes, Messrs: Letter to (re Don Quixote) Contents: A penciled annotation (probably by the book dealer who sold this material to Albert Boni) at the bottom of the first page states "re Don Quixote", Aug 18, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Wilshire, Gaylord: Letter to, photocopy, Sep 30, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 25)